[Music]
thank you
hello everyone welcome to active live
stream number 47.2
it is August 17
2022 and I'll just quickly update the
video
now it's really August 17th we're having
our third discussion of the set of
papers in active Dynamic social
cognition and active inference and
active inference and abduction
welcome to the active inference
Institute we're a participatory online
Institute that is communicating learning
and practicing apply to active inference
you can find us at links here
this is a recorded in an archive live
stream so please provide feedback so we
can improve our work
all backgrounds and perspectives are
welcome and we'll be following video
etiquette for live streams
at activeinference.org you can find out
more about participating in projects
like the live stream and also a lot of
other learning groups and projects
ongoing
we're here today in our third discussion
around this dyad of papers both from
2021 active inference and abduction and
inactive Dynamic social cognition and
active inference so check out 47.0 and
47.1 for more background and to kind of
get
up to where we are now
let's go to the introductions and then
we're going to take it where it goes
so I'm Daniel I'm a researcher in
California and I'll pass it to Dean and
then to Stephen
thanks Tony I'm Dean I'm here in Calgary
um
uh I guess I'm still a researcher
although I'm a retired one um
basically this is this is an opportunity
to have one of the authors with us which
I think is fantastic and essentially
sort of take this from
uh all the things that we've set up to
now and get an opportunity to sort of uh
be it through the lens of of the authors
and so that I'm really excited about
that passively statement
thanks Dean so yeah I'm Stephen on
medicine Toronto
um I work a lot with spatial meaning
making
um participatory theater and dialogue
approaches and uh yeah I'm really
pleased uh to have the author here today
one of the authors and uh also to
for me I'm really interested in in what
we're doing here because of
um the ability to get Beyond what's
often just called emergence
um emergence through the Mind Body or
emergence through some sort of Loop
that's being explained in an action or
emergence that people just talk about
when things interact and something
happens well I I see this work with
abduction or the work with abduction as
being
um
a way to make a much more tractable way
for living
things that start to make things happen
be thought of and not just call
everything emergence so uh I I'm I I see
both these two as being
a big kind of black boxes that we can
maybe shine some light on and that would
help a lot of people so yeah I pass it
back
should I pass it to you Daniel first
well Majid go for it and just say
anything you'd like to any context on
the paper
I imagine I'm a philosopher of science
based uh in Encore or middle State it's
called University and I thank the
organizer for
this wonderful events and their for
their good and graceful discussion of
the ideas and and teams of the papers I
do not know if I can add anything that
has not been discussed already in the
past couple of sessions
uh so I think that this is
well there has been for the past few
years uh so I'm the second author of one
of the papers active inference abduction
and active inference and the other
author of The is
a renowned uh Charles Sanders Paris
School are so I I mainly can
take credit only for the parts that are
about active and friends I'm not an
expert in purse uh ideas or in uh
semiotics for that matter but I also
have been doubling from time to time in
my own semiatrics and I was
searching for a way to be able to ground
semantics in nature to be able to grow
semantics in natural world
uh which is very tricky because it seems
that to the extent that we are engaging
in natural processes we can see
mechanisms we can see processes but
meaning is something that emerges at
some point something that has not been
there before in the nature itself but
which which
doesn't completely sound right because
well it seems that everything has to be
come from nature at some stage but it is
not like a Continuum so I was thinking
of finding a way for
an action-oriented way for being able to
speak about meaning and representation
and well well the an activist embodied
approaches and Collective size and
philosophy of science are very well
established no but
to be able to grow semantics semiotics
in action we came to the conclusion that
active inference May provide a nice way
a nice way that is well supported by
what we know from in the sense of
computational Neuroscience and total
biology to be able to explain how some
linguistic Concepts some semiotic
Concepts can be explicated in natural
terms I don't know if any of that makes
any sense to you but it was what we were
trying to do in this paper and a couple
of other papers that we were composing
to altering together
excellent thanks for that context Dean
I gotta ask you a question so lots of
times when we're talking about semantics
we tend to see them written down on
pieces of paper as an example right but
when you say semantics in nature
um one of the questions that we've kind
of danced around but not sort of spoken
to directly is sort of semantics as
nature maybe semantics surrounding us
and the abduction paper really helped us
understand maybe uh the perspective that
instead of us moving towards and seeing
semantics or generating semantics us
being available to that information
around us what what's your sense after
after sort of
I don't know if you've embraced uh
Pierce's philosophy but after at least
engaging with it what is your sense of
what semantics are as nature as opposed
to
sort of embedded in nature
well
well uh
that's a very good question and also a
difficult one
well look so uh I actually didn't what I
was trying to speak about it was
grounding semantic in nature saying that
so uh sometimes I also think of our
environment our trade informational
trade-off with environment in semantical
term but
some other times I think that perhaps we
are reading what we think about the
world into the World perhaps there are
no meanings in the world itself I think
that if we want to be radically
naturally civil the war
um we couldn't so the natural world
doesn't contain semiotic in the sense
that for example artificial languages
human-made languages can contains
semiotics that much is I think more or
less obvious I think that we can't treat
semiotic into the nature the same kind
of Semitic that we can find in
human-made languages into the nature I
think that that's
obvious too on the other hand the things
that are made by human beings are in a
sense natural because human beings are
natural entities and
they have this kind of natural
capacities to be able to communicate
with another and with their environment
so there should be some sort of natural
base it could have just come from
nothing there it should be some sort of
natural basis for that which is
basically
I I like to think of that in terms of
human beings or the community of human
beings action-oriented interaction with
rather and with nature so if you think
of
semantic in this sense being thinking of
being
in semantics or being surging in
semantic or enveloped in semantic in
distance so I completely agree with you
because
uh I think that
even though it is not precisely a
well-stated semantics that we can find
in an artificial language there is
some sort of trade-off of information
between human beings between organisms
self organizing complex systems with
rather biotic self-organizing complex
system with other and with their
environment either individually or
collectively
and
I think that this provides a good
natural basis for also understanding
semiotics in the sense of the signs that
the interpret the soil interpreted
science that we use in writing books or
I don't know different source of
communication the more advanced ways of
communication
thank you Stephen
yeah thanks Majid I was wondering when
you're talking about these
more advanced forms of communication or
biological ways of
having semantics whether that's far more
entropic far more
dispersive than what would happen when
we think of it in our
traditional literature of uh words and
uh ways that we would have ontologies
and computers so it's a kind of
some other is it an a a completely
different process or is it like another
flavor of what's your thoughts on that
uh I'm sorry I was not quite clear about
what I was trying to say what I was
trying to say is this look
by speaking of the advanced forms of
communication I was intend to refer to
advanced form in comparison with the
rudimentary natural form so for example
the way that we are speaking together
right or the way that Dan is just
writing down the ideas on the screen and
that sort of stuff these are I think
that these are Advanced ways of
doing some sort of
semantic
conducting some sort of semantic
Enterprise because we can communicate
and by speaking of that in terms of
advance I just wanted to say that it is
more advanced that
I don't know the very basic cases for
example uh very basic cases that we can
see in the natural world so for example
how the signaling processes in terms of
um of biological uh terrorist biologists
cellular biology that sort of stuff so I
think that I'm seeing that in terms of
some sort of theory of evolution how
creatures or how self-organizing systems
start to communicate with either and
with their environments even at the
level at the cellular level or at the
level of population of cells or neurons
or whatsoever so there are the
rudimentary ways but at the same time
there are more advanced ways of
communication meaningful communication
such as what we do in human societies
whether in terms of individual or what
we do in libraries institutes and
recently in terms of human artifact
interact so it was whatever and I think
that this story the main story what
what persuaded us what motivated us to
look into active inference was that we
wanted to find some sort of natural
basis for that and you are completely
right again we were thinking of that in
terms of uh in terms of the entropy of
system keeping the entropy of this
information entropy of the system within
the bone so in for so for the like
everything else that
has been constructed around the notion
of active infants have free energy
principle the core of the story is that
in order to be able to maximize the
chance of their survey world the
biotic cell for organizing systems have
to be able to
keep their entropy or their surprise
within the bones and in order to be able
to that they have to be able
to find ways to optimize their moods of
communication and I think that this
provides a basis for a basis for
uh the generation of semantics so in
order to be able to maximize the chance
of survey world we we need to be able to
gets to some level of competence and
reaching that level of competence seems
to be impossible so I think that to the
extent that this story is action
oriented to the extent that it tries to
grow semantics in nature or semiotics in
nature I think that this completely
faithful to the pre to the pragmatist to
the Persian Origins but then again I'm
not an expert in that field
yep thanks like what I heard there is
that active inference helps us find
patterns across systems
by Framing them within a common
lens of keeping their entropy or their
surprisal bounded in engagement with
their environment which can include
other entities like themselves or just a
niche more generally and maintaining
that survivable bound
homeostasis and all of the variants that
we've discussed in other times
it's going to have different features
and cells bodies computer programs like
a computer program is a specifically
constructed entity where one extra
parenthesis or period
is going to lead to a halt but this
continuous embodied and inactive nature
of the biological engagement the
biosemiosis
which is what is pointed to in the
formalisms that we saw in hippolito and
Venice paper again the only formalisms
they brought in the paper rather than
citing out to were about things changing
Through Time continuously
and so yes for sure maintaining the
bounds of computer programs in a digital
and in a fragile setting is different
than maintaining the bounds of
survivability for like a cell or for a
linguistic entity
and they are different but they can't
even be said to be different unless we
have some ways of juxtaposing and
contrasting them
so Stephen and then anyone else
yeah thanks thanks for that Clarity
there Majid there's one thing that I
think also this ties to and I think
um having this move from semiotics into
like this
broader kind of unifying theory of Acts
of influence is really interesting and
it speaks to some extent as well to the
um when you say advanced communication
it speaks to what we often think of in
complexity work around complex and
complicated
so it's like organisms and life has this
complex adaptive non-linear processing
and then there's these kind of simple to
more and more complicated ways of
engaging the niche to
to do things to have
sort of systems of performative action
using objects using in in the case of
words that can also be seen as objects
so there's this kind of parallel
Evolution between complicated
things being manipulated and simple
processes of things being manipulated
and the complex
sort of non-linear adaptive processes of
the uh that's all going on underneath
all of that
all right
very well look
there are a bunch of technical Notions
such as complexity and
I I try to speak of this in terms of the
basic ideas that I have in terms of
philosophy of science because I'm
basically a philosopher philosopher of
science so then I speak of more advanced
form when I
and what I have in mind in terms of
sophistication of ideas I don't know
whether it could be translated into the
technical notion of complexity but I'm
saying that like that look so there is
interaction between
organisms so take the individual fish in
the in a school of fish or take the
monkeys you know hold of monkeys or uh
or Bears or anything that of that sort
and they have to be able to communicate
they have to be able to try to make
sense take two bears that are trying to
sing to to perform a duet to sing from
the same human uh they are trying
to so it seems that they are engaging in
some sort of harmonious activity in
order to be able to do that they have to
be able to communicate in a successful
way that all together minimizes the
overall entropy of the system
information throughput of the system no
by speaking of more advanced form I'm
not not only thinking of these simple
forms of communication between Birds and
other kinds of organism but
but in terms of the sophisticated
cultural forms of communication that we
use poetry so not I don't know
scientific theories which usually come
especially in case of science come with
very
sophisticated theoretical and
mathematical sometimes formulation
notation and you're completely right
again they demand
the right amount of manipulation because
you need to always test the theories and
and and confirm them or falsify them so
this kind of Engagement between human
beings also
mandates a great amount of manipulation
because it is not just on the basis of
transfer of pure information that it
takes place but most of the time through
manipulation of the environment which is
also
engages artifacts other than other
agents so and this is how we think of
this sophistication or complexity of the
situation by thinking of that in terms
of the advanced forms of the cultural
practices such as such as what we
observe in mathematics literature and
science which are still meaningful which
are which are still in
involving a great amount of semiotic
Enterprise semantic and Enterprise but
we need to be able to explicate them in
simple natural forms of communication
like what we observe in the natural form
and what like what we hope to be able to
be explicated in terms of minimization
of free energy and minimization and
keeping the information throughput of
the system within bonds
it's a different thing to maintain the
not better or worse but merely different
to maintain the survivability of a
biofilm than a data center
yet we want to approach them in a first
principles
grounded compatible interoperable
scientific lens
and so that is what perhaps
brings in active inference so Dean and
then we'll continue
yes yes just with regard to the last
thing that Dan said there is another
collaboration uh I mean there's another
co-author paper that is by me and afti
published in
of
I think that the European general for
philosophy of science and it is about
the explicating methodology of science
which also includes abduction and
inference syllabus explanation and other
sort of stuff on the basis of
uh active inferences so uh yeah you are
completely right this is and in many
ways this project to be able to
explicate methodology of science at the
individual and social level
on the basis of this first principles
given all of the skepticism that there
exist about trying to engage in first
principles in life sciences it sounds to
be a very ambitious project but it seems
that where we are now and I think that
uh
I'm going I I think that this is a pro
this is a project Wars pursuing but I if
if there is time I will come back to
that later
excellent
Dean
this is awesome um I gotta I got a
question for you because I think you
could probably answer this better than I
could I'm still wrestling with this one
so if I'm if I'm a person who's trying
to perform some kind of a situational
analysis
try to determine what the functions and
the purposes are in the setting in which
I exist
I can look at that in terms of a
semantic space but what abduction
I think
um introduces is the idea idea of
semantic time and and I'm so glad that
you sort of pointed to the fact that
Daniel's typing stuff out right now this
is semantics time for him he's actually
generating some semantics even as we're
talking so I guess what I'm wondering is
if we're gonna if we're gonna look
through the lens of active inference as
the situational analysis lens do we
separate out what Daniel's doing when
he's typing from the nature of what
we're doing right now or do we see them
as so sort of Co
-compatibilities that's
I don't know the answer to that I I kind
of I'm leaning in the direction that
they're they're kind of inseparable they
they orchestrate something that doesn't
happen if we only have one or the other
what are your thoughts
well to to tell the truth I'm not well
uh uh sorry my phone was ringing and I
lost Focus for a moment but
uh and I do apologize for this it was
there is one of the reasons that I was
hesitating to
uh join but
well
uh could you uh I do again I apologize
to ask that but could you elaborate a
bit on the last part I hear that price
what I want to get more familiar with
the last part sure well the semantic
space is stuff I think is is really
material like you can see Daniel typing
things out across that slide it's but
what I think curse asks us to
contemplate
is the actual semantics time the actual
change or shift of what's actually
happening in that moment and so I was
wondering if we are not just looking at
active inference as the object of our
attention but we're actually
inferring what is going to happen next
do we have to include the idea of what's
Happening
not just semantically as as a product of
what's typed out on the page but as a
process and what does that what does
that then imply in terms of what we can
um
what we might be able to pick up quicker
in terms of our our
um embedding in these different contexts
that we otherwise wouldn't be able to
pick up if we only had one or the other
it kind of starts moving us towards this
realism anti-realism debate which I'm
still not sure it should even be a
debate but that's me and my relativity
shortly what I heard there
unmute is semantic spaces have been
extremely characterized not completely
but before active inference long before
people have done embeddings of sentences
and meaning Concepts in semantic spaces
without a temporal aspect
and so I heard a question about
abduction as providing a framework for
semantic or semiotic time whether with
the two-stroke engine of generating and
selecting hypotheses or the action
perception Loop or a few other ways
look very well I think that that's a
very good question I put only in order
to loan one's own trumpets I put the
paper that we wrote in the chat box and
this is I think that this is precisely
about this point because it is about
selecting hypothesis the process of
select selecting hypothesis look and I
do not know how to relate that directly
to induction to or abduction but what I
try to do is to say this that at least
in the so-called Advanced forms of
communication or abduction that I told
about what's important is not only what
we are doing in the moments but what's
important is or estimation of what's
going to happen later next so and this
is I think that it is very important in
terms of charge centers first logic of
not only logic of science but also
economics of science when he says that
we have to try to find a way to invest
in theories in hypothesis that have a
chance to being a winner in a long time
so in a way time enters the process
because we have to be able to have a
long time view on how the abductions
that we are going to construct lead to
fruitful results not only at the moment
but in future possibly long future
especially if you are engaging in some
sort of sophisticated
sophisticated process such as scientific
uh practice or such as Theory hypothesis
construction or hypothesis testing
time plays an important factor and
what's important about active inferences
especially the forms of active
inferences that could be
appeal to so when we just become active
inference perhaps we didn't elaborate
that much on the
abduction and active inference paper
although we refer to that but in the
other paper I think that we have been
referring to that quite a lot the thing
is that the kind of active inferences
that
are useful in this context are active
inferences that are taking place on the
basis of temporarily Rich models but
Christian and others mentioned as models
that have some sorts of temporal depths
or temporal richness which basically
allow the organism to have a perspective
have some insight not only on
prediction of free energy or pre sorry
minimization of free energy or
minimization of information entropy but
also have some insight into
the efficiency of its
processes it's he's Pro it's practices
for minimizing free energy in the long
term so I think that it comes back to
the issue of temporal depths and
temporal richness which is also is
related in a very interesting way to the
issues of Consciousness ourselves with
other topic that I'm interested in so
this is the thing there are some biotic
self-organizing systems that can engage
in some sorts of social activity uh and
this self-organizing systems happen to
also have this wonderful capacity to
form abductions that are informed that
that take the
uh
temporal aspect into account at the same
time the same group of biotic
self-organizing systems that are capable
of Con making this kind of abductions
inferences are also
capable of having cell food and
Consciousness and self-consciousness and
that sort of stuff so in a way it comes
together the ability to be able to form
this kind of abduction that allows to
choose the hypothesis hypothesis that
have a better chance to bring good
hypothesis in the long run and the
ability to have self or
self-consciousness and at the same time
the ability to form
foreign
models that have some temporal depths or
temporal richness so I think the
temporal depth is at the root of that
all because it allows us to make
policies and it allows us to have some
strategies some
strategies that basically enable what we
can think of in terms of scientific
methodology in terms of philosophy of
science that I'm interested in
if I could add a note there then pass
back to Dean and thinking about the
similarities and the contrasts with
different biosemiotic systems so a
signaling protein or signaling molecule
might have a tremendously rich and
contextual biosemiosis like a hormone in
a certain way might do various different
things relationship with a cellular
context so what I'm hearing with the the
more rudimentary forms or the
non-abductive forms
of communication and the relationship
with their temporal depth is that while
there is a conditionality to the way
that hormone is received
and there's an instantaneous complexity
or complicatedness
it doesn't necessarily have a temporal
depth in the semiosis it might play a
role in a temporal depth like the
hormone could play a role in
developments but the interpretation of
that
hormone is instantaneous
in contrast with linguistic
communication
even before we get to this level of like
speaking to the distant future or
invoking the distant past or different
timelines and metacognitive awarenesses
there's a space of interpretation
between the herd sound or the scene
symbol itself
and
the way that it triggers internal
Cascades which must involve temporal
depth like a word alone
a phoneme alone is not conveying that
same impact of meaning
as the hormone binding and so the
increased cognitive complexity of like a
linguistic entity
opens up a space of interpretation for
the words
that brings in the temporal depth and
differences in acculturation and
differences in what people have learned
whether they even know that word at all
whether they know about how it's being
used by that person and so in the
linguistic
semiosis
we can see how it has analogy to other
forms yet also
contains a space where also active
inference can be used to start to
disambiguate and to build models of
Dean
thanks Daniel um
first of all you you almost grabbed what
I was about to say but I'm going to say
it in different words
um this question again around that
abduction paper
I don't have the exact quote up here but
so paraphrasing one of the things that
in the paper that you point out is that
pierce understands that if you if you
don't see the triadic if you don't see
the three kinds of logic has taken it
together the deductive the inductive and
the abductive you're kind of missing
what he was trying to alert us to my
question is so when we break it down
further from that if we reduce it to the
Adaptive inductive and abductive we
don't leave it as a whole as the as the
as the way of looking at all of the
Logics started working in concert
is that
is that looking then at logic as a tool
is it looking at it as instrumentalism
if we if we take it down to that
reductionist place I know that if we
leave it up at all three together
working in concert that's realist and
that's the part that I very much agree
with in your paper but then my question
was you guys never really talked about
this if it's taken down to those more
simple relative Logics over time are
each one of those Logics then could we
see them as actually being instrumental
oh well I'm not sure that I can
answer that question because I'm as I
say I'm not an expert on pairs but I
can't say my own perspective
um uh so was I was genuinely interested
in was in
engaging with pers ideas was the part
that was about abduction
so perhaps I was
I don't know no that's a think of that I
do not know why I was so interested in
abduction but nothing deduction or
induction but perfect because inference
is the best explanation abductions are
seen do seem to play an important role
in philosophy of science but uh well it
seemed that philosophers of science just
take deduction and induction for granted
and perhaps it is because
well I can't defend their I can't defend
that decision I I don't know whether we
have to I have to at least to spend more
time to say deduction induction but
um about these Logics or at least this
kind of inferences being in sterements I
don't see why they couldn't be
instruments in a way if if I want to
stick to
the jargon of distributed cognition and
embodiment and activism the things that
I'm pursuing no I think that we can
think of them in terms of cultural tools
like many other kinds of cultural tools
that we can use in order to pursue our
intellectual
of course whatever that intellectual
quiz is out there to be pursued so I
think that we can think of them as
instruments so
the main question I think that because
you also mentioned realism and
arterialism the question is that if we
think of these things as instruments
would there be any room for being
realist about this kind of approach is
that related to the question of realism
what do you did you want to say what do
you want to say do you want do you want
to relate that to the question of
realism
yeah I actually actually do I think as I
said when I read when I read the paper I
think the argument that says that if we
if we look at Pierce's work as anti-anti
nominalism non-nominalism I believe when
it's written in its complexity State and
the relationship between those Logics
it's the relationship between those
Logics that it's examined yes I very
much agree you can't describe that as
anything other than realist
my question is is that if we reduce
below that is that when the
instrumentalism
percolates that's my question all right
very well look uh so uh this is my
perspective on realism in this context
is this
look
so we are speaking about uh semiotics
and we are speakable the semantic
aspects of language and interpretation
and that sort of stuff the question is
that where this kind of interpretation
where this kind of semantical
interaction with the world is coming
from uh I think that if if we can't see
that it is not something arbitrary that
this is something that is not developed
or chosen on the basis of convention not
only conventions but conventions that
are feeding on
if there is some objective element on
that that in that it is not it is not
instrumentalism it will provide some
basis for realism so and they are
semiotic and semantic aspects in for
example uh constructing scientific
hypothesis or theories or scientific
practice and that sort of stuff right I
think that to the extent that we are
able to grow on this semantic and
semiotic aspects in nature to the extent
that we can provide some sorts of
down to earth
's natural explanation for the emergence
of this semantic and Semitic element we
could defend some sort of
realism so then again you may ask what
source of realism is that and I can't
say that this is a source of realism
that that
is informed by all best scientific
theories so it is some sort of radically
naturalist
that I think would be kind of compatible
with pragmatists and personal ideas so I
think that they're they're really take
comes from the fact that we try to grown
semiotic and semantic the logic of
abduction induction deduction all of
that we try to find natural processes
that enable those kind of inferences and
to the extent that we can find natural
processes that are explicated in terms
of so always scientific theories there
remains some room for defending a
version of realism that Willard van
Orman koi used to call robust realism it
is robust in the sense that it depends
so
instead of trying to latch onto mind
Independence science Independence
realities into the objective world this
kind of realism draws its force from or
best scientific theories and I think
that this is real it is real it's in the
sense that we can provide the naturalist
story we can threshold some natural much
naturalistic story some some science
scientific story of the psychological
grown the mechanisms that enable this
kind of inferences
awesome thank you thank you
Stephen and then I'll add a note
um
thank you when you mention so you
mentioned the scientific process and
almost the the the deductions the uh
inductions that can occur with a Model A
scientific model that's been created so
which is slightly different to say the
um the the what's real for me at the
scale at which I can perceive
um as a human
um and see things my model might be able
to see things
slightly beyond what my sensorum can
perceive in my experiential ecosystem I
like to use the term experiential
ecosystem of being alive
so when that's the case is it almost
that these models are given some sort of
agency some sort of sentience
that what's real for the model in a way
um very well oh well
that's a very good question in order to
try my best to provide an answer to that
I may need to drift away a bit from the
scientific context and engage in some
sort of philosophical discussions that
might be a bit boring for
for the audience I'm not sure about that
but I will ask you to try try all right
no giving some sort of agency to model
is is an interesting question a question
that as it happens I think is worth
taking seriously
but it might not be directly related to
so look in order to be able to defend
some sort of mod in order to to to
Advocate some sort of model based
version of realism you do not
necessarily need to give agency to
models and because
in order to be released you the thing is
this the is the nature and the structure
of scientific theories is so complicated
that we cannot defend realism on the
basis of some some sort of perceptual or
sense perception evidence so the the
evidence for scientific theories if you
think of that in terms of model-based
science doesn't come in terms of sense
perception because the construction of
scientific theories is much more
complicated than that there are
different kind of so there are different
kinds of experimentation manipulation uh
uh theoretical Distortion idealization
you name it so when we speak of models
there are different kind of things that
make it very hard to
to think of the model-based
representation as some sort of direct
relation so we cannot defend realism
about models in terms of
relating sense perception or sense data
or something directly directly to the
models uh there are other kinds of
Virtues that we may want to depend on
and most of the time philosophers of
science do not agree on a specific set
of Virtues that could build they usually
speak of considerations of Simplicity
fruitfulness uh personally that sort of
stuff uh efficiency but usually they do
not agree on a specific set of set of
Virtues but one thing that they agree
about is that
models do not receive confirmation on
the basis of
their feet with sense experiences
because oh it seems that for modern
science or mother think of that in terms
of quantum mechanic things not only that
but different sorts of Sciences is
becoming so theoretically complicated
or scientific models are becoming so
idealized and theoretical entities that
feature in these models are sometimes so
sophisticated that it will be futile to
try to find some sort of
perceptual or sensory evidence for that
right
so
well
and again when we speak of abduction and
when we speak of inference to the best
explanation I still think that inference
I still think that active inference
could eventually or could at some point
lead to
at least grown some methodology of model
selection that allow us to on the same
basis on this more or less on the same
basis that Charles Sanders Paris speaks
of logic of science or economics of
science can lead to some sorts of
methodology of science that allow that
that could allow us to select
scientifically first of all models
models that deserve to be given a chance
were realist as things that are
providing a more or less reliable image
of the universe
uh videos depending directly on sense
experiences
thanks there's there's a lot there
one of the
most key pieces of I think the
juxtaposition of these papers and how
we're seeing the discussion around
science and realism and enculturation
progress in 2022.
is that and to connect this also to this
area of the semantic spaces and semantic
time which abduction requires it's at
least two phasic so it has to it can't
both be happening in the same instant
the same um unit so the question of
realism
and
especially on specific constructs within
the broader apparatus of free energy
principle like focusing on the blanket
construct Marco blanket first and
blanket Etc
it's often been approached in terms of a
question of compositionality of space
as you put it like mind independent does
this exist physically well what do you
mean by the table exists physically I
mean it's there when I'm not looking or
if I don't believe it's there it could
still hit me
in the mine independent situation
first off there's a massive challenge in
re-minding that system the whole hard
problem of Consciousness or even just
simply hard problem of biocognition or
semiosis and so in that setting it's
very defensible to take a instrumental
perspective on the meaning of semantic
spaces
when we turn from a compositionality of
mine independent physical space
into a compositionality of meaning as
enacted in the pragmatic sense what's
real is action
then
the commitment to mind Independence
being lifted
we have actually a
multi-perspective cognitive scenario
that naturally embodies
questions of symbiosis
because meaning as enacted is model
dependent
and so
I'm sure there's a lot of like loose
threads or other ways to go but again
it's a large turn for me to see the
discussion evolve from being about mine
independent physical
interpretations as being the Crux of
realism
and the pragmatic shift as opposed to
like the materialist or the reductionist
stance
and the pragmatic shift
reintroduces mind or really just removes
the kind of filter or the dam and just
lets mind rush back in
so there's really a lot there and then
you connect that all the way to
active inference grounding methodologies
of model selection
and I think in that
domain it inherits greatly on
a huge amount of statistics and machine
learning work on policy selection for
example like using a free energy
functional and minimizing it to scan and
evaluate and make a decision upon a
space of affordances and policies
is what has been happening in control
theory cybernetics and so on even down
to the evidence lower bound and the
forms of the free energy functionals
that are used
are broadly related to exactly model
selection processes
so just like if we were doing a linear
regression we might want to fit the
least squares error and if we were doing
a Bayesian model selection we might want
to use like a base factor or a Bic or
AIC Criterion
here we're in the space of
mind based cognitive entities active
particles
and so
active inference provides a process
Theory
that is able to
make all of that come together and make
sense
and then this paper
connected it to the qualitative
though rigorous and structured
framework of abduction and kind of fit
like Abduction into the ignition
instead of the inductive deductive
which can be limiting in certain
contexts
Stephen
just just wanted to pick up back on when
you mentioned about model selection
um
so that's interesting in the sense that
there's there's policy selection in
active inference okay what policy I'm
going to take on my action
I suppose you can look at what regime of
attention will I use and will capitulate
my internal model
but I think a lot of times an attempting
this is often thought about
um in active inference but really the
model selection May well be the the
external artifact or the
like
um like like uh Magic was talking about
this scientific model
is
um is different to say the model
selection that's happening in terms of
maybe types of generative models that we
might think of in the brain
and can have its own you know it can
exist someone could write a paper like
uh Pierce and you know it wasn't
published and people pick it up 50 years
later and it's recapitulated into a
system of of meaning making
um so I think this there's um
the the the the ways that models get
selected and then
how they can be used and maybe
couched in a system I think it's really
interesting and maybe that system is
also we've talked about this before and
is when that system doesn't need to be
alive anymore to function like can there
be a dead system I.E a computer system
that can then or how much of it becomes
not dependent on the living so that's
just just one point that I think you
know comes back to that question of
um you know where is It ultimately
grounded
thank you Stephen yes Majid
uh I I think that unfortunately I have
to start to leave and I do not want to
open a can of War before doing that but
I want to uh briefly speak about what
Stephen mentioned right would for
example and I want to
stay with the example that he provided
for example the person being dead Char
Sanders players being dead but the ideas
of being picked up look then I was
starting to think of scientific practice
in terms of active inference
in the book that I wrote in 2019 uh
people started to make very significant
criticism and meaningful that
active inference is the theory of
individual brains but scientific
practice is not an individual activity
it is not something that science is not
taking place in the brain of individual
individual people it is some sort of
social activity it is distributed in in
in scientific groups and scientific
Commodities so and then
I get more deeply engaged with this uh
literature on distributed scientific
cognition in terms in terms of works of
Ronald gear and uh some other people and
I found it very interesting so uh look
um the model selection
scientific model selection uh some sort
of advanced form of
cognition Finnish form of cognition is
grounded I still think that it's
grounded in active inference but it
doesn't need to take place at the level
of individual scientists it could be
distributed to the community of
scientists and then the issue of
minimization of entropy could be
understood in terms of minimization of
collective entropy of scientists or even
minimization of the
Collective entropy of the couple
commodity of scientists and their
environment and I think that it leads to
some sort of revolutionary understanding
of the nature of scientific theories
because we usually think of scientific
theories as a class of propositions or
set of model Authority or set theoretic
models in terms of mathematics but if we
broaden this hopes a bit to think of
theories as pieces of informations
pieces pieces of knowledge that are
dispersed and distributed in scientific
Community or things that are that emerge
through the interaction between
scientific Community or scientific
scientific group and their environment I
think that it may lead to very
interesting it very interesting
perspective on the nature of scientific
theories as well so in a way I was
hijacking this discussion of active
inference because I was too because
being being trained and bred as a
philosopher of science I mainly
interested in in some internal issues in
philosophy of science and when I speak
of scientific realism I think of that in
classical
classical terms and philosophy of
science being realistic about the target
system of theories and scientific models
but I think that it still leaves ample
room for also being realists about
active influence itself but for
different reasons and for reasons that
are much more sophisticated and
complicated than uh could be could be
unpacked directly with relation to mind
Independence reality of active
inferences or or whether there are such
things as first principles in mind
independent War so I think that of
course there are no such things as first
principle mathematical first principles
in if you open up brain and nervous
system you can't find first principle
mathematical first principle you will
find different kinds of tissues and
mechanisms and other kinds of things but
I think that these two concerns about
realism about active inference and free
energy principle and my own concern
about scientific realism about Target of
scientific theories that could be
selected on the basis of active
inference could be related together at
some point but I have to apologize this
is a joy to participate in this
discussion and I have to apologize for
for
being pushed to live abruptly
it's excellent Majid we appreciate it
and the dot three is yours when the time
is right
thank you very much it was very nice to
meet all of you I'm going to leave yeah
take care
wow
okay we'll take a deep breath and then
we'll continue or maybe you don't even
need to breathe Dean go for it
well I just love the fact that the the
term hijacking was introduced not by me
because that one of my biggest fears
around this dot two was was hijacking
something and I I think I I think I
understand what he means by that because
it actually feels that way if if you
if you look at what we were just talking
about which is active inference could
ground a methodology of model selection
let's just assume for a second
abductively
that it does it can and it does
well what would that mean
well what that would mean is is
literally changing the directionality of
what we typically perceive and as he
pointed out we can't let our perceptions
conflate what we are perceiving with
what whatever reality is and I think
we've all
agreed that that's that's dangerous
thing to do however
in in the spirit of what what
could active inference ground in terms
of methodology and then in terms of
models collection my my question is
typically typically in the outside world
as we're using scientific principles we
start with an idea hypothesis a process
and we turn that into a product some
kind of a materialization Stephen and I
were actually chatting about this before
we came on the live stream today that's
what we see that's what we sometimes
label the reality
what active inference as active
inferring
suggests is the mark of blanket stays in
the middle between the generative model
and the generative process however if we
were to actually contemplate that active
inference could ground a methodology and
does
we would actually say that the
generative model is the product or is
the materialization and as we pass
through the mark off blanket we actually
move to to
different versions of
of
process one is relativity the other is
relationship and together that forms a
new absolutism so that is literally the
emergence and that's kind of where I
started in this I haven't sort of been
not explicit in hung my my backside out
there to have a whole bunch of people
take a bite out of it but if if
we I think are courageous enough and
take the risk and we look at that
differently than how we traditionally
looked at it that process leads to
product another way of describing that
is product and process but we actually
look at it as processed in product
meaning we start with whatever our hard
evidence is as a generative model as
product
and then from that we gain insights and
intangibles and things that we call
structure
because we understand now the
relationship and the relativity and
those new absolutisms that would be the
condition under which active inference
actually does
ground model selection what do you guys
think about that
it's a nice angle
I'd like to move to the images that
you've prepared and see where that comes
back
so let's return to the initial
juxtaposition slide that we looked at in
the dot zero yep with iceberg
um okay so again I'll put our our video
chat as the tip of the iceberg
we raised many points of contact
between these two papers and then
you've provided
um a graphical abstract we could say
that we're going to go through now
and then from that graphical abstract
we're going to enter into one or more of
these comparisons
and see how they are structured in
relationship with the general abstract
which we'll see now so here we are
what is happening on this slide
okay so Inez recently had
um
there was a YouTube clip where she was
talking I think the topic of the
conversation was the three energy
principle in the edge of chaos and one
of the quotes that I pulled was she made
the statement making this bridge
logically sound because what she was
looking at was
uh some of the some of the debate that's
been going on between realism and
attributes
and of course in order to be able to
uh talk about those things she spent a
lot of time looking at free energy
principle and how that works and she she
did a really brilliant job of sort of
trying to make a case for why the debate
was taking place why she and some of the
authors that she works with have taken
the position that they've taken
um what I think that us bringing two
topics like that that's been focused on
in action and social cognition and
abduction if we bring those things
together approximately which is what
we've done in this live stream series we
could actually show how
potentially you can move from a place
that says well if I'm all about the
realism
um then I can't be anti-realist and vice
versa
uh I think what if you're in a position
where you're trying to help people
understand not what they see outside of
themselves as a product going through an
assembly line like somebody who's
learning and then they come out the
other end and they're now all assembled
because they've gone through a process
if you actually start out as seeing this
human living system has a product that
is made up of things
that are already present priors and
posteriors and all of these actions that
it can take as an agent and you actually
move
from the left of that bottom
bottom left corner diagram to the right
you can actually use the inaction in the
abduction and the anti-realism and the
realism as placeholders within a Markov
blanket setting and as you move through
time and as I put passing through time
as in depth of field of some of those
memory traces that you are pushing
through your working memory and pulling
out from your long-term memory as well
as literally the river of time flowing
you could move from an idea of
this is the this is sort of the platform
product or stability the grounding from
which I start and as I become more and
more familiar with what I'm analyzing
situationally I can actually pick up
the relationships the entailments and
the Rel the Rel the sorry the
relationships as relativity and the
relationships as entanglements
and so that is acting as an active infer
as opposed to looking at and through
active inference lens so that's what I
was trying to pull together here because
as it says in the middle of this slide
as active infer says predictionary
reducers across all processes not just
subject matter one of them could be
active inference as a tool or as a
non-tool
when is active and then this was we've
already talked about the witness of
semiotics when is active inference both
a partitioner and a framer and when is
it also a filter so looking back through
time and then pulling from the memorial
and projecting out into the future
how do we how do we
keep the complexity how do we keep the
triadics how do we avoid the Trap of
reducing down but they're not being able
to build back up to the complexity scale
where the reality actually exists
because I think if you if you if you
cross a certain threshold and you get to
the operations level of course it's got
to be tools of course it's got to be
instrumentalism but then it's got to
come back to and I think Dan Daniel you
mentioned this earlier it's got to come
back to so what about that table that I
bump into
is that not real and so I think it's the
ability to sort of go below the
threshold and then resurface back above
it's being able to understand what the
actual outer boundaries are and what the
rows and columns and their ability to
differentiate are and I think if we
wanted to as I said I don't want to
hijack but if we wanted to we could show
how both the inaction
and the logic application requires us or
are at a minimum at least gives us the
complexity state from which active
inference which was it's kind of the one
thread that holds all of this together
retains that sense of okay it's both
anti-real and real at the same time
thank you Dean Stephen first
yeah deep breath
so yeah I know she's really this is
there's a lot here and this is really
powerful and I think
I think the idea of moving
room
these ways of interpreting anti-real
realists so that moving through or
moving through an action abduction I
think that's helpful
um and the idea that you know how that
passing through happens what we're
trying to do is pass through
almost a trough a bit between the two
um and there's this idea that there's
maybe a couple of Roads we traditionally
have this High Road low road but um it
can be
I I see it's also
um the way that we structure
that understanding
of abduction of inaction of realism
is shown up in our idioms it shows up in
the way we structure our language so I
mean to what extent if we're passing
through the middle here right through
the middle
and I'm saying is and if I was to go and
on my left as a road on the my right
there's a road
and the road that's left to be explored
or the road that's forever giving and
revealing the left field is the inaction
the abduction and what's right
is my anti-real reel I mean it's either
anti whether it's real bright that's
right
as as they say in North America a lot so
I think there's um
there's this way that we're sort of
trying to engage with these ideas as
practitioners and researchers and
um
kind of interdisciplinary
sort of uh connectors which starts to
become itself structured
um so I think this is this diagram is
quite helpful to to start to tease out
some of that
um in again maybe a kind of an inactive
way
thanks
I'll make a few comments and then let's
jump into the comparisons and see how
this image is applied
so the epistemic foraging the journey
The Learning Journey all of these have a
temporality and so just wanted to
quickly note that that connects very
much to our discussion on semantic space
and semantic time okay if there's a
space to be semantically exploring
but we're taking a path in it then first
off Dalton and Maxwell at all's path
formulation of active inference is a
natural fit
and we need to consider the Oneness and
as we've talked about when there's clock
time with Chronos and then there's the
timeliness with Kairos and so that
epistemic Journey we don't need to deny
or even take a realism or not stance on
the chronology
we do need to take a reality of that
journey in the abductive semiotic space
with time
then
Stephen you brought in this road and
path
metaphor and so
one thought there was these are like
signposts like they're labeling the
quadrant
but we kind of have a cultural norm that
actually that quadrant is all labeled
it's not only labeled underneath the
word and
so when we have a signpost
and we say we're going along this road
that doesn't mean you just gravitate and
collide with the signpost in fact we're
always like moving between and among
signposts and then I just thought of
someone saying like I'm in the city I'm
as close as you can be to the one pin on
Google Maps or something like that but
actually even these labelings have a
diffuse of aspect to them
so outside of important and clarifying
scholarly debates
where we are like with both feet on one
label and trying to knock others off
their perch with both feet on their
label which we looked at in the sort of
Survivor context previously
the people in the audience and in the
crowd and the co-creators that the
hippolito and Venice paper really
artfully focuses attention on
it's like what about the fact that
social cognition is distributed in an
active and in culture what about that
they're in that trough between the
signposts
so those are a few aspects um and then
one last one was like Dean you mentioned
relation as relativity and relation as
entanglement and it makes me think about
as as this Legend helps us see aspects
of
edges can mean different things we look
at a lot of base graph representations
where edges have a certain
interpretation in a statistical
framework but even then with effective
functional and anatomic connectivity
we've also talked about different kinds
of edges
and now here we're in the space time of
semiosis
and there are edges and some of those
edges reflect relationships
amongst nodes and others are
entanglements so the um ankle bone and
the knee bone might be like entangled in
the physical real world whether we know
about that link or not there's something
to it that's real in the sense that
Majid is using realism and then there's
also a relationship with a creative
enough forger amongst everything because
you can say the relationship between the
ankle and the field of astronomy is they
both start with the letter A or you
could do any other number or this is
just not that that's the simplest
relationship is they're not the same
thing or they both are related to the
same thing
it's General it's not always a useful
statement to make well Forks are not
spoons okay but utility is just one of
the virtues or the criteria by which we
might evaluate a certain epistemic path
and our harshness on grading or
evaluating epistemic paths doesn't
always have to be extreme and there
doesn't have to be one rubric either so
there's so many Connections in that
space
pragmatism and the productivity and the
social setting where all productivity is
ultimately embodied
brings pieces in
that are
hopefully
of epistemic and pragmatic value
let's go to the comparisons or do you
want to stay here do you no I just want
to point something because in order for
the comparisons to make sense I have to
kind of okay context
so these arrows I want to just say
quickly the interdirectionalities
results from limits or constraints
things we've used Expressions upper and
lower bounds
and bi-directionalities result from
parallel processing things like
arbitrary parameterization which blew an
eye and used talked about a lot last
week the arbitrariness of that
then the question becomes does a bridge
right as an idea remain a bridge as a
materialization as entailments things
like the relatives part that Carl talks
about the parents and the children and
and we've been talking about this a lot
and entanglements meaning the
relationship of same and different
so how does that play out typically from
an academic way of producing that is to
start with well we've got to come up
with a process we've got to come up with
a methodology to derive a product
what I'm suggesting active inference
does is it starts with a whole bunch of
products it's like what it is and and
Thomas talked about in their paper you
you co-construct
that's social space you start with a
product and then you learn
how to translate and interpret one one
other quick thing
um if you on the other side of this
paper it says
a Marco blanket is a scale-free
statistical tool yes yes yes it is and
in Majid and and and Addie's paper in
order to state state stay in a
non-equilibrium city stay within Barbara
with its environment an organism must
regulate its internal entropy the Markov
blanket of a node consists of its
parents children and co-parents that's
all true so it depends on whether you
start with a product and move to the
process or whether you start with the
process and move to the product and
that's where
things really open up an optionality
really becomes a thing with active
inference or at least that's what I'm
trying to argue
also in that I saw a bridge not as just
the thing that you drive on but a bridge
is a stance it's a position like a back
bend and it's a game
and in that interpretive space
is the difference between the signaling
molecule at the cellular level and human
linguistic communication so not to
return only to that but in that space we
can respect
whatever LED that generative model of an
S to say that and mean that and it's
always going to be a yes and with our
interpretation
and to the extent that there are
anti-virtues of model comparison
speaking for another cognitive entity
could be something like that because
you're never going to escape the fact
that it's your framing still of their
intentionality
so how are we going to take that as a
starting point rather than shut the door
on discussion because of that being a
real feature of social discourse Stephen
yeah
um and this sort of further to that
product process
and how that fits and
potential bridges that gives Dean can I
just ask you you
saying as well this this links to the
idea of the model in again we're coming
back to the idea of modeling rather than
the model
um
so with active influence you you know
you're
you're not you're not wheeling in the
Trojan Horse with a model that you're
going to take out you're you're you know
you we're bringing in a modeling process
where the product can be
um retro
interpreted almost or reverse engineered
or somehow so then maybe there's
something in that we don't you know
would that make sense to what your
your talking about so so again it's
easier to put down a critical path
because people are familiar with that
right like this is the things these are
the steps check these boxes and this
will be your result all Libs is doing is
showing the inversion of that and what
the possibility is so I'm agreeing with
you Stephen how do we bring both into
people's front of Mind attentional space
because I think it's both that are
dancing with one another as we are
figuring
something out if we want to follow
that's that's a that that doesn't
require both but if we want to forage or
stigma stigmergicly arrive at a place we
don't know other than as an abstraction
even the I don't I don't want Daniel
you're the expert at this but I don't
know what the abstraction is for an aunt
that that has faith that whatever they
are doing in terms of following that
trail is what they were put on this Good
Earth to do
the puns will come but I might even say
that that's how ants are
let's go to the first comparison okay
is remove the limits if you notice all
four of the red lines on the outside of
the previous diagram have been removed
because this was the enactive social
cognition paper and essentially what
this does is divide up that space it
takes the generative model and allows it
to now be categorized if that's what you
want to do if you want to move from the
triadica of abductive deductive and and
inductive
this is how you actually create those
different
subcategories within the larger picture
so there's a quote from their paper from
mines and Thomas's paper it's possible
to understand active inference in two
ways a realist view that the properties
of the model constructed by applying
activities tools should be also be
expected to exist
sorry has an ontological property in the
scientific phenomenon we're trying to
explain
a non-realist view that the model uses
simply an instrumental tool once applied
to some activity allows the scientist to
draw interpretations and explanations
and then they go on to talk about why
they use dynamical systems theory so we
already talked today about so what
happens when you cross a threshold does
that when is that when complexity arises
versus when you're below the threshold
and that's when something different than
complexity exists and so my my argument
would be yes you can have something
that's complexity and then you can have
something that's complicated and tools
and tools and instruments are still
complicated don't get me wrong there's a
huge technical investment that you have
to make in terms of being able to make
them function but the note that I wanted
to put down here was
is causal order being explicated not as
some generality as in I'm being imaginal
now on some abstracted level but rather
as a specific place in time
the relational causality patterns from
which context and Longevity and I love
Majid without any prompting talking
about temporal depth we started down
that path to live streams ago
there can be gapped can actually be
addressed as placed in that in that
distribution right because we respect
both difference and distance within the
collective as a new scale as
relationally caused now actively
inferring
which includes selection from with and
in a distribution the counter factual
which if
this is this goes right back to what
Majid said about we could use it as a
grounding for the model selection
is not only able to function as a tool
but of selection by the selector
processing the action taker with the
real Realm by the free energy principle
so we must first deconstruct meaning if
there's anything within this that needs
categorization and separation we can do
that in order to co-construct or choose
choose how to move from a product to
this is entailing that or this is
entangled with that
all we have to do is see it without the
bounds or the horizons
same image one last thing
let me contrast that with two slightly
more technical notes the first is
um figure 9.1 in the March 2022 active
inference textbook
this is what's described as The Meta
Bayesian perspective and so here the
outer shell
is the experimenter and the experimental
context that they're providing in terms
of stimuli and then the behavior that
they're observing of the entity in
system and they are making a cognitive
model of an entity so this is cognitive
modeling as a process that's one aspect
and it can be an active inference
process from the experimenter
without falling into the all Minds our
scientists
um fallacy that yellow brimberg has
adequately sketched for us even in 2016.
but we can still see an active inference
framing of the outer experimental Loop
and use compatible Frameworks for
modeling the inner cognitive Loop and
then one other uh note there
with this last section of what you wrote
is when we're using the active block
furnace package which is implementing
active inference in cadcat a complex
systems modeling framework
CAD CAD enables parameter sweeps
so you can have a parameter inside your
simulation 0.1 and then you could test
and run a bunch of simulations
concurrently or in series like what if
it were 0.1.2 0.3.4
we've also thought towards using active
inference exactly in this metabazian way
because the parameter sweep space can
become vast if you have hundreds of
parameters the sweeping across 100
dimensional spaces is massive the space
is large
which actually motivates an imperative
for searches and that brings timeliness
back into the picture through the
scientific modeling process in finite
lives finite resources and so on
where we're using active inference and
finding optimally informative
experiments of parameters to test
about the inner system
and so this is like
a case where in the visual graphical
analytical framing shown here in
figure91 or in the computational
implementation with active block fronts
in both of those technical settings
mathematical and computational
and then this setting whatever it is
that's on this slide all of those are
showing it's not even just like left eye
open right eye open this is binoculars
we're not just switching the monocle
from one eye to another it's actually
able to be like wrapping and gripping
itself
in this way Stephen
thanks if you go back to that previous
slide that ties to this from the
textbook
um
I don't know if you still got it there
the testing image yeah
um
the
there's where it says subjective model I
would imagine
that itself could be called you know
might be thought of as an instrument of
sorts or a modeling process there's
there's a question about how this can be
interpreted and this is is useful maybe
this is a sort of a bridge
is even within this it's like well
um subjective is an interesting term
um where it's actually now being modeled
out where is it objective where is it
um
where where would that then be in terms
of
you know is it a case of
really getting a feel for these
parameters as they sweep you find the
sweet spots you find that um
scale friendliness that starts to emerge
could be enough I mean that could be
what a lot of organisms are doing as
well although it's refined obviously
through Evolution but you know as you
sweep it is what pragmatically gets you
where you need to be as opposed to being
real values that have been aimed for
um so you get into this interesting loop
I think that Dean was showing there
between the realism anti-realism I mean
there might even be times to break
realism to get out of that hard lock and
say this is really what's going on no
it's a sweep
to find a scale friendliness it's a you
know Dean was going to say something I'm
going to pass it over no no no I just
love love this because without any sort
of prompting that that diagram that I
put up I don't know when when Carl
built that diagram
I know when I built mine and and then
and ported it over to this set of slides
it was many many years ago and the thing
that I always said to people who I
shared it with and I tried to unpack it
and explain it was I want you to
manipulate it well the Fantastic thing
is many many times Daniel in his
capacity as as host moderator of these
live streams he takes information and he
manipulates it which is exactly what I
had participants in the programming that
I was doing actually do because if it's
left as a representation and the person
isn't allowed to move things around and
actually play with it then they have to
take they have to they I'm imposing on
them or the person reading Carl's books
and Carl's representation that that
process
to product like there's a product now in
front of you that's already been
established and now you're interpreting
that but every time you manipulate it
you actually start by creating your own
product first and then through the
manipulation discover the relationship
and the relativity so one of the things
whether it's Carl's representation or my
much cruder one
it's still when when the person picks it
up and literally sweeps through it
Stephen as you were described having it
that's when the inversion actually takes
place if you leave it static if you
leave it as a bridge
and then you don't get a chance to move
it around and manipulate it and
re-represent it in through your own
inaction
that's when it that's when we tend to
get I mean some of us are super bright
I'm not one of those people that's why I
had to give people like me
the opportunity to say don't just leave
it on the page
play with it do something with it enact
it into your own set of comprehensions
so here's a little
evocative image meme but let's to
complete the comparison we discussed how
we had the open Edge quadrant model here
and some quotes from the an octave
Dynamic paper now
we're going to go to the next slide
where the bounding of the red is on the
outside of the
Visual and we're taking quotes from the
abductive paper so what quotes did you
highlight from the paper and what does
the change in the visualization
represent okay so first thing they see
is that the rows and the columns have
disappeared and all we've done is made
sure that there's those those edges on
the outside so just to confirm that
so remember this is just comparison one
there there were six comparisons between
these two papers that I pulled so so I
want to make that clear too but on this
first comparison uh just to show what
the difference is between an edgeless
and an edge constraint this is
especially the case this is a quote now
from from Maddie and and she's paper
this is especially the case that we
assume that the development of markup
blankets by friston now he clapped
Kristen blankets unlike the original
characterization works by Judea Pearl on
probabilistic causal networks admit of a
realist interpretation
of the relationship between the organism
and the environment while the role so
it's variability retained the role of
the concepts of the Markov blanket and
pearl blankets and many treatments are
the free energy principle is an
instrumentalist one whereas in Pierce's
even stronger terms can see to anomalous
interpretation of meaning for instant
blankets are realists not only in the
non-instrumental sense but also in the
sense of being non-nominals entities the
modal terms of references are two real
possibilities such as what's conceivable
or produced by imagination
anticipatorially related to the Future
states of Affairs are used in making
sense of the key aspects of the theory
we will argue in this paper the three
energy principle has been put at the
center of a viable picture of an
organism's insight into the consequences
of its action and its ability to choose
the best or most efficient strategies
that contribute to the Fulfillment of
best possible consequences so not just
consequences now but over a temporal
field and all I noted was realism is the
philosophical position that posits that
universals are just as real as physical
measurable material nominalism is the
philosophical position that promotes
that Universal or abstract Concepts
uh I just lost my place sorry
I just made a new line abstract Concepts
do not exist in the same way as physical
tangible material from instrumentalism
to Insight and insight or minimum two we
talk about that all the time because
we're talking about relational and not
just relative
to rule
we build categories
we generate hierarchies and eventually
we see patterns to model and regain an
Insight then the pattern is tested from
Audi there's another paper that I read
about is it's fantastic called the new
light on Pierce and I quote it from that
this is what Pierce had in mind when he
wrote lady Welby that's reasonable to
adopt a given a hypothesis reasonable
all right
if it will be wise to go to some expense
to put the hypothesis to test dependent
upon the advantage that that would
accrue from knowing the truth of the
hypothesis from that testing result of
consistency I.E repeatability comes
Universal things like laws rules actions
Etc that's the step that in my diagram
is on the right hand side
this is the entirety of the pro it is
the entirety of the process real yes
because it's complex
a reality made up a process so some of
which have no basis in reality again
from the new light on Pierce again
Addie's paper the fourth Memoir entitled
analysis of the methods of mathematical
demonstration opened with the
affirmation that his first real
discovery about mathematical procedure
was that there are two kinds of
necessary reasoning the collateral and
the theoretic theoromatic
easy explained as follows collateral
deduction is where
it is only necessary to imagine any case
in which the premises are true in order
to perceive immediately that the
conclusion holds in that case the
aromatic deduction is deduction in which
it's necessary to experiment in the
imagination upon the image of the
premise then in order
from the result of which experiment to
make sorry
collateral deductions to the truth of
the conclusion so again
this kind of hints that if we
remove too many things and reduce too
far
we're we're left with nothing but
instrumentalism
So within those within those bounded
contexts that we've now arbitrarily
parameterized there's a whole bunch of
things that we can pack into that silent
and those things can move around and
Float around in there they're not
constrained to the upper right and the
lower left corner now all of a sudden
those bi-directionalities are indicators
of just how much fluidity is going on as
we pass from product
and sweep across to Insight
[Music]
thanks Dean let me add a thought here so
just for reminder and reference other
resources you'll find so much more but
deduction is the inference over about
particular instances by referencing
generalities laws and principles
induction and contrast is where we go
from what we've observed with the
instances up towards forming
generalities so deduction going down in
that kind of a top-down framing
it's very interesting that the deduction
is split into two components here
you said collateral I believe and I
think that may be totally valid but I at
least would read this as corollarial
of or related to a corollary well what
have we heard nowhere else but here and
elsewhere active inference is a
corollary process theory of the free
energy principle
so
from a more General principle
in the definition
the corollarial deduction
is a situation where a case is only
needed to be imagined
really imagined
where the premises are true
propose a blanket where there's a
particular entity and the blanket is
separating them from the generative
process in such and such a way such that
the entity is a generative model and the
internal states are doing some kind of
mode tracking or path tracking of
external States in a cybernetic good
regulator framework
the premise is merely a premise it's not
the culmination
so that's what we see in the corollarial
deduction
all you have to do is consider the
premise to perceive immediately that the
conclusion holds in that case well yes
if you propose setting up the base graph
to be truly just that way
as a corollary of the free energy
principle then
that is already like a story arc that's
been completed
no one's saying that you wrote the paper
or that you had the startup that's
profitable but also no one can say that
it's incorrect that you made a premise
that kind of
um completed its Arc and then in the
second case we're still within deduction
however it's necessary to experiment in
the imagination so thought experiments
which we can
Place into a setting of mental action
and attention and counterfactuals
counterfactual generation requires the
generation of counterfactuals ergo it is
abductive it requires a generative phase
and a selective phase so we're going to
generate and select that's the abductive
loop that's happening with a when in a
semantic space
as part of this theoromatic deduction
and then the results of that experiment
can be used to make corollarial
deductions to the truth of the
conclusion
so that's kind of
counterfactuals on imagined premises
and guess what it's real
Stephen
can I add one question in there
um
we have our make our deduction from a
particular instance and
we abduct
the kind of
best policy selection
when we induce generally this induction
I see that as kind of a narrow in the
Gap often like there's a there's a
generality and then a bit like
reinforcement learning might try and do
um
you're inducing uh between
and
that's often what we see is most visible
you know someone's trying to re you know
reduce the Gap in in the physical world
with the product that we've got that
we're manipulating
um because that's kind of what we can
see I was speaking I think earlier to
Dean about this you know someone's
making a pot and that you know they have
the piece of clay that goes wobbly and
they're sort of making it into a pop you
know so there's kind of like
they're inducing inductively trying to
make it closer and closer to something
that's more like the general idea of a
pot
but that's what we see
and we would at some point we might not
know what they're even doing then
suddenly we deduce it's a pot because
like you say there's a particular
instance of being a vote but behind all
of that there's
um abductive processes at the biosim I
don't know whether the word biosemiotics
is the term actually I'm still not quite
clear how to how to put that in there
but
um I think that fits in with what you're
saying I wonder what your thoughts are
on on that sort of inductive take
me
if I can just highlight how this
comparison one relates to the realism
instrumentalism and the The Clay Pot
creation
um
so here we have the quadrant separated
again totally speculating working with
Dean's uh graphical artistry
in
one totally defensible and absolutely
scientific framing
the viewer of the pot construction could
see their entire logical apparatus and
inference about what is happening
as an instrumental
process happening I'm not saying that
they're really making a pot I'm just
saying that's a socially constructed
term and it's totally contingent on my
enculturation what I believe is a pot
maybe they're making a piece of art who
am I to say that it's um not something
else maybe it could be used as a hammer
so
that places the inference about the
system at the Forefront
and provides clarity as well as openness
the edges of the drawing are open
because it does leave a lot of
structuredness surrounding the origin
Point again but also room to go off in
many many directions
what Majid returned our attention to was
the
nature of observations coming from the
generative process coming from the niche
if it's whimsical as I think he said
well then yes instrumentalism is fine in
its totality however if it's not
Whimsical If there really is a table
that you're going to get hit by if that
is really something that you're buying
if that is something with limited
resources we're doing are we making a
pot or are we making a pan
then
the boundedness
is now moving to that scenario
which includes the the mindedness of all
of the entities one entity is not
speaking for the other
but that entity is seeing the situation
as real in that it is truly providing
pragmatic
implications
for survival
and its real meaning it's really
biosemiotic meaning
and so
here the boundedness is more around the
situation
and in that space in that room
there are paths amongst the theory
where if you go to a different situation
you cross the line now crossing a line
is not like always a bad thing but all
of a sudden if someone's daydreaming
about a totally different topic they've
exited the situation
but within the situation there are a
diversity of approaches
here the situation is actually being
used just as an experimental context for
a theoretician or a researcher in their
removal
to be able to consider
different ways of modeling
so I'm not sure if this is consistent or
or you know Dean Orthodoxy or heterodoxy
but I see the boundedness as
allowing for that Center of action
to be approached in a pragmatic not a
theoretical
but not academic approach whereas by
making the divisions cutting nature at
the joints and like oh wow those joints
correspond to long-standing
philosophical debates in Academia who
knew and maybe they don't always
correspond to those joints
yesti
I know we're getting we're getting close
to the end here but so thank you for
explaining that in your words that helps
me because I I'm always curious to
whether or not the things that I'm
trying to share actually are making
sense to other people and it sounds like
maybe is is gaining subtraction I want
to say this one thing
um before we have to sign off here
traditionally in most academic settings
uh and I'm as guilty of this as anybody
because I was a curriculum designer
for a part of my life
um we start out
trying to figure out how to construct a
plan
and I think what active instruments
affords is this idea that instead of
instead of reconstruct a plan and then
others follow it called a curriculum
what this potentiates in addition to
that this is not dismissing that or
saying that that doesn't have its time
and its place what this does is ask us
whether or not we could forage a plan
could we figure out how to fly how to
build the plane on the Fly
that's all this is is entertaining
so that you actually have both so when
you're Sully and Hudson River has never
traditionally been a landing strip
it becomes one but you need both you
need to think and to do you need the
action and the abduction
and so if you if you limit yourself to
one or the other for the sake of not
being cognitively overloaded I get that
that's the deconstruction piece but if
you are foraging for a plan the plan
falls out
of a product your priors meld with your
priorities and then it becomes
self-evident what the plan is as opposed
to somebody handing you a list and then
you simply following
so I I wanted to get that in before we
uh have to call it a date but I think
that's important to sort of
put put that context both in gripped
and as gripper because it's it's no more
complicated or simple than that
thanks we are on our last slide now we
got through one of the six comparisons
and the six were the tip of the iceberg
of the tip so
we know that we can never
line your eyes
or vocalize everything that needs to
occur but
we also carry on
so we can pause here
reflect on
the last three videos in this series
forty seven zero one and two
where to now
how are we different after 47.2
than before
47.00 Dean
my suggestion is that when we reflect we
are literally inducing we are literally
looking back at the entire narrative or
Continuum or whatever you want to call
it and trying to figure out what just
happened
so yeah and I think that's when a lot of
the stuff that's that's
not instrumentalist turns real I don't
think people actually get a real sense
of real until they do the reflection
the classical scientific communication
public speaking advice which I look
forward to seeing how what Majid shared
about economy of research also
reimagines the doing and the
communication of Science of course but
some of the classic advice is tell them
what you're going to tell them tell them
and then tell them what you've told them
we can turn that into a bit more of a an
active or a planning based
framing like
consider what is about to happen
abduction
during the live stream think about what
is happening attention
and then after the live stream consider
what happens
reflection
all of those processes are happening in
the dot zero one and two of each
sentence of each person
speaking turn
in the videos and not all these
different scales
that's as real as anything
so it's really a nice
hopefully sequence that we've engaged on
and there may be more decimals to come
on 47
certainly 48 and Beyond will also carry
forward in this
historical way
in which
when we talk about Concepts Beyond 47
we'll have this shared basis
of bringing abduction in and so on so
Stephen any last thoughts
yeah I'd like to thanks for going here I
think
we've had enough traction to show that
there's a lot of value in
trying to wrestle between
um and
there is
um as well as that idea of the
scientific you know like Daniel you
mentioned the scientific
communication where you have something
that's quite clear to communicate
there's also
when it's opening up
a space for something that could go down
multiple
different routes once it's
contextualized so I think this speaks to
contextuality situatedness
and May and may require and may require
some um
I I'm interested in how this may require
some non-verbal kind of more
um
experiential processing to like of
certain cases to to explore so I think
that might be open up the potential to
sit in between and just take something
from here and say okay what would that
be like experientially and just grooving
that so that's something I'm gonna
explore what that might be like
Dean penultimate words
I want to thank the two of you again for
creating a kind of in Stevens Point a
kind of a safe space to take these kind
of risks because again we're not we're
not just sticking to the script we're
kind of maybe triangulating off two
scripts and that that isn't always that
doesn't mean that you're always going to
be right I mean like people come back
and say wow were you ever wrong about
this I get to learn but I think before
that opportunity even arose prior to
that there were two people that are now
sitting on my desktop here who who
shared in that
risk analysis effort and I want to thank
both of you for being so supportive
around taking this kind of uh uh let's
hang it out there and and see who
salutes and who takes it down because if
it's taken down I'm I'm I'm okay with
that too but just being able to have the
opportunity has been spectacular in
terms of developing how I think
that's not what you can do for your
corollary process Theory
see you fellows later thank you thank
you